只有富人才能在这个国家做生意
Only the rich can do business in this country.
因为这条路上有许多巨大的陷阱
Because there are huge pitfalls along this road.
小贩和商人很容易就走进陷阱
A trader or a businessman can easily fall into them.
在这条路上诚信和努力工作是不可能成功的
It's impossible to run a business on this road with honesty and hard work.
但是有一个办法..
But there is a way...
一条捷径
...a shortcut.
这条捷径直通德里的议会大厦
Which goes via Delhi's parliament house.
有了关系，你可以做任何事情
With connections, you can get anything done.
重要的是，谁是你的关系网..
What's important is, who are your connections...
他们的地位有多高
...and how high up they are.
他们的影响力越大..
The more influential they are...
你的生意就会越做越好
...the higher your business will soar.
我也有一张德里的权力关系网
I have also paid my respects in the power portals of Delhi.
我和德里的关系是悠久而深厚的
My relationship with Delhi is old and very deep.
在91届选举期间..
During the 91 elections...
我们给这个政党捐了很多钱
...we gave a lot of donation to the party.
一大笔钱
Large sums.
从政党顾问到首相，每个人都知道
And everyone is aware of this, from the party's advisor to the Prime Minister.
所以当补选日期宣布后
And so when the by-election dates were declared...
我和萨哈布谈过
...I spoke to Sahab.
我去向他致敬
And I went to pay my respects to him.
英德拉吉·夏尔马
Indrajit Sharma.
首相联合秘书
Joint secretary to PM.
他是安排会议的人
He was the one who fixed the meeting.
那天是1991年11月4日
The date was 4th November, 1991.
“我在想，首相为什么要见我? ”
[Harshad]'I was wondering why would the Prime Minister meet me?'
“他会跟我谈什么? ”
'What will he talk to me about?'
但他知道我的一切
But he knew everything about me.
他一见到我就说..
As soon as he met me, he said...
“哈沙德，我党视你们为朋友”
..."Harshad, our party has seen you people like our friends."
“我们可以一起做一番大事”
"And together we can do bigger things."
但现在，警察和中央调查局
But today, the police, CBI...
还有政府的其他部门，都只追捕一个人
...and every other agency of the government is only after one man.
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
Harshad Mehta.
为什么? 因为我诈骗？
Why? Because I've done a scam?
不，原因是..
No. The reason is that...
我很了解这个国家的总理
...I know a lot about the country's Prime Minister...
还有这个党派的其他人
...and about many others in this party.
我知道真相
And I know the truth.
由于巴布里清真寺被拆毁，暴乱仍在继续..
Riots are going on because of the Babri Masjid demolition...
但我的家人更怕 CBI 而不是暴乱
...but my family is more scared of the CBI than the riots.
中央调查局可以对我和我的家人做任何事
CBI can do anything to me and my family.
我拍这个视频是因为，如果我出了什么事..
I am shooting this video so that, if something happens to me...
人们应该知道幕后黑手是谁
...people should know who is behind it.
你在干什么，米什拉？
What are you doing, Mishra?
怎么把他打成这样？
How much did you hit him?
你没长脑子吗？
Is your brain between your legs?
看看他的脸，像钟上的6:05一样倾斜
[Madhavan] 'Look at his face. It's tilted like 6:05 on a clock.'
布尚不是一个呆子
Bhushan ji is not a goon.
如果他说得清楚，我就让他走，但是他不愿意开口
If he spoke clearly, I'd let him go. But he's not willing to talk.
我该说什么? 我应该说什么语言？
What do I say? In what language should I speak?
你们这些人到底懂不懂？
Do you people even understand anything?
布尚先生，你不是呆子
Bhushan ji, you're not a goon.
你是个混蛋
You're a p**p.
你和你的老板把市场搞得一团糟
You and your boss have turned the market into a br***el.
“对吧? ”
[Madhavan] 'Right?'
谁能理解混蛋说了什么？
And who understands what a p**p says?
只有妓女
Only the prostitutes.
看看他们，他们像妓女吗？
Look at them. Do they look like prostitutes?
用他们能听懂的语言交谈
Talk in a language that they'll understand.
- 这是商业语言...-闭嘴！
- This is the language of the business... - Shut up!
生意... 生意... 生意！
Business... business... business!
你当我们是白痴吗！
Do you think we are a******s!
我们知道你是做什么生意的
We know what business you do.
看看他们，看看他们的脸
Look at them. Look at their faces.
他们只有一个目标，那就是击败哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
They have just one goal and that is to sc**w Harshad Mehta.
但那是不可能的，所以在那之前..
But that is not happening, so till then...
我们会搞死你的，明白吗？
...we'll sc**w you. Got it?
如果你明白了... 开始说吧
If you've understood... Start talking.
’说’ ，’说’ . . 我该说什么？
'Talk', 'Talk'..? What should I say?
“小声点! ”
[CBI Officer] 'Lower your voice!'
你看起来很生气
You seem angry.
别生气，布尚先生，这是我们的工作
Don't get mad, Bhushan ji. That's our job.
去拿条毛巾，拿条毛巾
Go and get a towel. Get a towel.
看他流了多少汗，你快把他打成肉酱了！
Look how much he's sweating. You have beaten him to a pulp!
“别生气”
[Madhavan] 'Don't get angry.'
去拿毛巾
Get the towel.
擦擦脸
Wipe your face.
继续，擦擦你的脸
[Madhavan] 'Go on, wipe your face.'
这是什么？
What is this?
怎么了? 你在上面撒尿了？
[Madhavan laughs] What happened? Did you piss on it?
你们是中央调查局的员工还是一群狗？
Are you the CBI, or a pack of dogs?
你想在哪儿撒尿就在哪儿撒
You piss wherever you like.
我让你用水把毛巾弄湿，不是用尿
I asked you to wet the towel with water, not with piss.
你甚至不知道怎么审问
You don't even know how to interrogate.
至少，提出正确的问题
At least, ask the right questions.
我们问错问题了，是吗? 好吧
We are asking the wrong questions, is it? Okay.
我们会问正确的问题
We'll ask the right question.
米什拉，什么是正确的问题？
Mishra ji, what's the right question these days?
伊路，伊路... ..
[Mishra] 'Ilu, Ilu...'
伊路，伊路
Ilu, Ilu.
伊路是什么，伊路? 对，我应该问你吗？
What is Ilu, Ilu? Right. Should I ask you that?
伊路到底是什么? 我该问你这个问题吗？
What the f**k is Ilu Ilu? Should I ask you that question?
你能回答吗？
Will you answer that?
该死的混蛋
F*****g p**p.
现在我只是用尿擦了你的脸
For now I've only wiped your face with piss.
如果你耍小聪明，我就直接在你脸上撒尿
If you act smart, I'll piss on your face.
如果哈沙德知道了，他会让你们所有人付出代价的
When Harshad finds out, he'll make everyone pay for it.
让我离开这里
Let me get out of here.
德里在他的掌控之中
Delhi is in his pocket.
是的，哈沙德是老板，对吗？
Yes, Harshad is the boss, right?
德里是他的囊中之物
He has Delhi in his pocket.
我会把他从德里带来的所有人都关进监狱，明白吗？
I'll put all his p***ps from Delhi behind bars too, got it?
你能让首相..
Would you put the Prime Minister...
... 也被关进监狱？
...behind bars too?
出去走走
Step outside.
你说什么? 首相怎么了？
What did you say? What about the Prime Minister?
你疯了吗？
Are you out of your mind, Madhavan?
你知道你在说什么吗？
Do you have any idea what you're saying?
先生，为什么你看起来很惊讶？
Sir, why do you look surprised?
我们又不是在月球上找到水
It's not like we've found water on the moon, sir.
这个我们一直都知道
This, we have known all along...
哈沙德可能有很大的政治关系，仅此而已
...that Harshad might have big political connections. That's it.
哈沙德的一个手下告诉你，首相支持他
One of Harshad's men tells you that the PM backs him.
那么，你现在要去突袭首相府？
So, you're going to raid 7 RCR now? Huh?
你为什么对首相这么着迷？
What's this obsession that you have with Prime Ministers?
先生，根据我以前的经验，我知道..
Sir, from my previous experiences, I know...
不可能突袭首相府
...that it's not possible to raid 7, Race Course Road.
但是，先生，我们至少可以开始初步调查
But sir, we can start a primary enquiry. At least that.
-马德文，你不是认真的吧-我是认真的先生
- Madhavan, y-you're not serious. - I'm serious, sir.
我的幽默感完全与政治无关，这个案子正在转向政治
And my sense of humour is completely apolitical and this case is turning political.
听我说完，先生
[Madhavan] 'Just hear me out, sir.'
我百分之百确定，布尚是可以开口的
I'm 100 percent sure, Bhushan Bhatt can be our approver.
如果我们多招待他几天，他就会开始讲所有的细节了
If we host him a bit more, he'll start singing all the details.
“就是这样”
[Madhavan] 'It's done.'
你得悠着点，马德文
You need to slow down, Madhavan.
[ Das ]“让我想一想”
[Das] 'Let me think it through.'
悠着点，长官? 我们就快成功了
Slow down, sir? We are almost there.
这是托管人要求的资产清单
This is the list of assets that the custodian has asked for.
我让狱卒交给你签字
I'll give it to the jailer. Sign them.
房产、汽车、股票..
Properties, cars, shares...
兄弟，他们已经把所有东西都查出来了
Bhai, they've have attached everything.
他们把雷克萨斯也写上了吗？
Have they attached the Lexus too?
别想了
Don't think about it.
一旦你出来了，我们再挨个收拾他们
Once you are out, we'll deal with everyone.
别担心
Don't worry.
有中央的消息吗？
Any news from Swami ji?
我们已经给了他很多钱
We have given him a lot of money.
吃的人得到庄稼，收获的人得到上帝
He who eats, gets the crop. He who reaps, gets God.
不管我什么时候给他打电话，他的门徒都说他在冥想
Whenever I call Swami ji, his disciples say he is meditating.
说他会回电话的
That he will call back.
我不知道他要冥想多久
I don't know how long he is going to meditate.
现在，不要给任何人一分钱
Now, not another penny to anyone.
适可而止
Enough is enough.
告诉那些来自德里的家伙..
Tell those p**ps from Delhi...
- 我不会保持沉默太久-会没事的
- ...that I won't remain mum for long. - It'll be fine. It will all be fine.
别担心，照顾好自己..
Don't worry. Take care of yourse...
根据罪犯或被告的陈述..
Based on a statement made by a criminal or an accused...
中央调查局即将开始调查这个国家的首相
...CBI will question the Prime Minister of this country...
这样合适吗？
...would that be appropriate?
阁下，即使我们向马德文解释并阻止他..
Swami ji, even if we explain this to Madhavan and stop him...
这事也不会就此结束
...this won't end here.
达斯，当一个问题有很多答案时... ..
Das, when a question has many answers...
疑心总是集中在给出答案的人身上
...suspicion is always on the one giving the answers.
在这整个骗局中
[swami] 'And in this entire fraud, In this scam...'
“ ... 每个问题都应该只有一个答案”
'...every question should lead to only one answer.'
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
Harshad Mehta.
这是唯一的答案
This is the one answer...
公众和议会都会认可的
...that will be appreciated by both, the public and the parliament.
但我不知道马德文是否会同意
But I don't know if Madhavan will agree to this.
你俩谁是局长？
Are you the chief of CBI, or Madhavan?
还有一件重要的事
[Swami] 'And one more important thing.'
那个记者... 苏切塔
That journalist... Sucheta... Sucheta Dalal.
请你也照看一下她
Please keep an eye on her too.
有人告诉她一些
There is someone who is telling her things...
她不应该知道的事情
...she shouldn't know.
我觉得有人在跟踪我们
I think someone is following us.
先生，我需要和你谈谈
Sir, I need to talk to you.
好的
Yes.
我的几个手下被派去监视一名记者，长官
A few of my men have been asked to keep an eye on some journalist, sir.
- 记者?-苏切塔
-[Das] 'Journalist?' - Sucheta Dalal.
但这不是重点，先生，重点是..
But that's not the point, sir. The point is...
我的人力被用来做一些完全不必要的事情
...that my manpower is being used for something absolutely unnecessary and trivial.
你的人力？
Your manpower?
马德文，让我们先把这件事弄清楚
Madhavan, let's get this thing very clear first.
他们不是你的人
They are not your men.
他们是中央调查局的警官
They are CBI officers.
我知道，长官
I'm aware of that, sir.
经过这么多年的工作，我很清楚这一点
After so many years in service, I'm well aware of that.
但重点是这些警官正在调查的案子..
But the point is, the case that these officers are working on...
- 我是那个案子的负责人...-他们只是听从我的命令
- I'm the investigating officer of that case... - They're simply following my orders.
好吗？
Okay?
好吧
Okay.
如果是这样的话，先生，我想再说一遍..
In that case, sir, I want to repeat that...
完全是浪费时间和资源
...it's a complete waste of time and resources.
马德文
Madhavan...
- 先生-你知道..
- Sir. - You know...
我真的很欣赏你
I really like you.
我真的很欣赏你对这个案子的投入
I really like the way you're dedicated towards this case.
我也知道你是我们部门最好的
And I also know that you're the best in our department.
但是请你... 请你试着理解
But please... Please try to understand.
我想让调查重回正轨
I'm trying to get this investigation back on the track.
长官，调查从未偏离正轨
Sir, the investigation never went off track.
- 我不知道你在说什么-看在上帝的份上
- I don't know what you're talking about. - For God's sake, Madhavan.
这是一个金融骗局！
This is a financial scam!
因为你的私人恩怨，你现在正试图
Because of your personal vendetta, you're unnecessarily trying...
让这件事变得政治化
...to make this political.
私人恩怨，先生？
Personal vendetta, sir?
怎么个私人恩怨？
How? How is it personal?
你不能把无辜的首相拖进这个烂摊子
You just cannot drag an innocent prime minister into this mess.
不要因为他令你不快，你就要像之前
Don't drag his name just because he was not happy with you...
调查博福斯一样调查他
...the way you handled Bofors.
你有任何证据证明首相也在这个骗局中？
Do you have any proof against the PM in this scam?
告诉我
Tell me.
你只是按照某个仆人告诉你的去做？
You're just going by what some lackey told you?
他正在试图转移这个案子，试着理解
He's trying to divert this case, try to understand.
你只需要关注哈沙德，仅此而已
You simply focus on Harshad, that's it.
先生... 这么大的骗局..
Sir... such a huge scam...
... 如此巨大的金融欺诈，我们现在都还没有具体数字
...such a huge financial fraud, that we're still only estimating the numbers...
你却想告诉我哈萨德是凭一己之力做到的！
And you're trying to tell me that Harshad pulled it off on his own!
没有任何支援吗，长官？
Without any support, sir?
我想从现在开始，这个案子应该由我来负责
I think from now, I should be taking charge of this case.
-你说什么，先生?-是的
- Sorry, sir? -[Das] 'Yes.'
我要接手这个案子
'I should be taking charge of this case.'
马德文，我相信你会在中央调查局度过很好的职业生涯
Madhavan, I believe you have had a wonderful career in CBI.
我不想让这个案子成为你和中央调查局的耻辱
I don't want this case to be a personal embarrassment for you and CBI, both.
我明白，长官
I get it, sir.
先生，我也不喜欢尴尬
Sir, I am not very fond of being embarrassed either.
但我只想告诉你一件事
But I just want to tell you one thing.
你会很尴尬的，先生
Embarrassment is going to be your lot, sir.
人们会叫你鹦鹉
People will call you a parrot. A parrot.
你这是什么意思？
What do you mean by that?
我是什么意思? 鹦鹉？
What do I mean? Parrot?
长官，命令是从别的地方下来的
Sir, the order has come from someplace else.
你只是在重复它们
You're just repeating them.
鹦鹉经常重复它的主人说的任何话
And a parrot often repeats whatever its master speaks.
你是一只关在笼子里的鹦鹉，先生
You're a caged parrot, sir.
我会让事情简单一些，先生
I'll make it easier for you, sir.
我要辞职
I will leave.
我不是那种会听鹦鹉学舌的混蛋
I'm not the ass who will listen to a parrot.
我会把辞职信寄给你，祝您愉快，先生
I'll send you my resignation. Have a good day, sir.
听着
Listen, Madhavan...
想想你应该跟媒体怎么说
Think about what you will tell the press, because that is going to be difficult.
你要怎么向他们解释..
How are you going to explain to them...
为什么这个案子的调查人员在调查过程中
...why the investigating officer of this case was compelled to leave...
被迫离开？
...right in the middle of the investigation?
“你会说什么? ”
[Madhavan] 'What will you say?'
或者死记硬背主人给的答案，像鹦鹉一样重复
Or learn the master's answer by rote and repeat it like a parrot.
先生，还有一件事
And sir, one more thing.
鹦鹉也被称为他的主人的声音
A parrot is also referred to, as his masters voice.
所以，如果媒体称你为他的主人，不要感到困惑
So if the press refers to you as his masters voice, don't get confused.
他们还是在说你
They still mean you.
他的突然辞职会引发一些棘手的问题
[swami] 'His sudden resignation can raise some difficult questions.'
不，这不是问题
No. That's not a problem.
我会告诉媒体..
I'll tell the press...
他很失望，因为他的升职没有通过
...that he was disappointed because his promotion didn't go through.
这就是他辞职的原因
That's why he resigned.
有道理
[swami] 'That makes sense. Hari om.'
我给你开些药，定期服用
I'll prescribe you some medicines, take them regularly.
医生，这药有什么作用？
How will medicines help, Doctor?
看看这地方的状况
Look at the state of this place.
“在这里呆了这么多天，我真是受够了”
[Harshad] 'So many days in here have totally f****d me.'
你说过在这种情况下很容易获得保释
You had said it's easy to get bail in such cases.
梅塔先生，别担心
Mr. Mehta, don't worry.
调查局已经向特别法庭法官承诺..
CBI has given an undertaking to the special court judge...
他们的调查只能持续到7月30日
...that their investigation can only go on till 30th July.
- 之后你就可以走了-你确定吗？
- You're free to go after that. - You're sure, right?
是的，我已经确认过了
Yes. I've seen the undertaking.
很好
That's good.
我将在家里庆祝我的生日
I'll celebrate my birthday at home.
我还从来没有..
I have never stayed...
离家这么久
...away from home for so long.
听着..
Look...
我们可以羁押哈沙德直到7月30日
We have Harshad's custody till the 30th of July.
但我们必须确保他..
But we have to make sure that we have him for...
至少继续关押两个星期
...another fortnight at least.
尽可能多申请FIRs
Do one thing, file as many FIRs as possible, against him.
好的，先生
[CBI officer] 'Okay, sir.'
UCO 票据贴现案 PFC 交易..
The UCO bill discounting case, the PFC deal...
都要提交FIRs
File FIRs in all cases.
然后去法院告诉他们我们正在调查15到16家银行..
Then go to the courts and tell them we are investigating 15 to 16 banks...
我们需要哈尔沙德的帮助
...and we need Harshad in that connection.
我希望瓦里亚瓦法官会同意
I hope Justice Variava will agree.
[ CBI 官员]“好的，先生，我们该怎么处理布尚？ ”
[CBI officer] 'Okay, sir. What do we do with Bhushan Bhatt?'
布尚... 不会与哈尔沙德对抗
Bhushan Bhatt... will not go against Harshad.
他很忠诚，而且我们对他没什么意见
He's very loyal. And we don't have much against him.
所以，不要在他身上浪费时间
So, let's not waste time on him.
好的，先生
[CBI Officer] 'Okay, sir.'
不... 耐心点
No... Wait, have some patience.
哈尔沙德？
Harshad?
调查局要求延长羁押时间
CBI has asked for custody.
“还有15天”
[Ashwin] 'Another 15 days.'
接下来会发生什么，我们要等到13号才知道
What happens next, we'll only know on the 13th.
已经两个月了，他们的审讯还没结束？
It's been two months, and they are still not done with their interrogation?
他们不会再把他关起来审问了
They are not holding him for interrogation anymore.
他们是在找他麻烦
They're troubling him.
他们正在向他施加压力，迫使他认罪
They are pressurising him to confess.
希望他一个人背锅
They want him to admit that it's his mistake.
嫂子，上面也有你的名字
Bhabhi, there's a notice in your name too.
我的名字？
In my name?
是的，这是你和哈沙德名下的税单
Yes, it's a tax order in your and Harshad's names.
这张税单有多少钱？
How much is the order for?
一千... 亿卢比
[Ashwin] 'Ten thousand... crores.'
我们调查过的所有银行..
All the banks we investigated...
他们的账簿上有一个共同的名字
...their books have one name in common.
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
Harshad Mehta.
迟早我们会发现..
Sooner or later we are going to find out...
你是怎么独自完成这一切的
...how did you manage all of it on your own.
不过你最好告诉我们
But it'll be better if you tell us.
你在这些银行里贿赂了谁？
Whom did you bribe in these banks?
我没有贿赂任何一家银行的任何人
I haven't bribed anyone in any of these banks.
哦，是的! 你不用贿赂
Oh, yes! You don't bribe.
你为它创造了一个新的术语，叫什么来着..
You have coined a new term for it, what was it...
银行家时代，对吗？
Bankerage, right?
你以为..
Did you think...
中央调查局不懂你们的商业语言
...that because the CBI doesn't speak your financial language...
你就可以吹的天花乱坠？
...you can take us for a ride to the moon and back!?
“啊? ”
[Das] 'Huh?'
你指挥了这么大的一场骗局..
You've conducted such a big fraud...
我们请了一队会计师，却只能粗略估算涉案金额
...that we need an army of accountants just to get the estimates.
而你却装作是你自己……
[Das] 'And you're pretending that you pulled it off...'
... 没有任何来自这些银行的内部支持
'...without any internal support from these banks.'
我很清楚..
I know very well...
你在每家银行都有一个背景
...that you had a setting in every bank.
我没有任何背景
I didn't have any setting anywhere.
你所有的数字都是错的，完全不成比例
All your numbers are wrong. It's all disproportionate.
我不欠任何人一分钱，这是唯一的真相
I don't owe anyone a single penny and that's the only truth.
哈沙德，你让你的生活越来越艰难了
Harshad, you're making your life more and more difficult.
“你会烂在监狱里的”
[Das] 'Jail will become your permanent address.'
这是沟通的方式吗? 你可以打电话给我..
Is this a way to communicate? You could have phoned me...
我承认这是错误的方式，所以我在便条上道歉
I admit it's the wrong way, Suchetaji. That's why I apologised on the note.
但我别无选择
But I didn't have a choice.
中央调查局全天候监视着我们
The CBI has eyes on us 24/7.
他们可能在窃听我们的电话..
They might be tapping our phones...
也许你的电话也被监听了
...maybe your phone is also being tapped.
毕竟，你和这个案子也有关系
After all, you are connected with this case too...
政府呢? 他们把我们当恐怖分子对待
...and the government? They are treating us like terrorists.
我害怕加州调查局会杀了我兄弟哈沙德
I'm scared that CBI might kill my brother Harshad.
他情况很不好，我得告诉别人..
He's in a bad state. I had to tell someone...
为什么是我? 你可以去找其他记者？
Why me? You could have gone to any other journalist?
- 我怕我会失去我的兄弟...-你为什么要告诉我这些？
- I'm scared I might lose my brother... - Why are you telling me this?
你担心你弟弟? 可是那些人怎么办..
You're worried about your brother? What about those people...
那些一生的积蓄和家庭都被你哥哥毁了的人怎么办？
...whose life's savings and families have been ruined by your brother?
把这些人的故事写出来不是更好吗？
Won't it be better to write about them?
求你了，苏切塔..
Please, Suchetaji...
‘开门，是我’
[Rahil's wife] 'Open the door, it's me.'
我一个人在外面
'I'm alone out here.'
快进来
Come in quickly.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
我不是叫你从外面锁门吗？
Didn't I ask you to lock the door from outside?
我们还要被锁在里面多久？
How much longer will we stay locked in?
我该怎么办? 告诉我
What should I do? Tell me.
每次我一出门，他们就来找我要钱
Every time I step out, they harass me for money.
上次他们威胁要杀了我
Last time, they threatened to kill me.
不，我知道他们不会真的杀我
No, I know, that they won't kill me.
他们会把我交给警察
They'll hand me over to the police.
警察还没有放哈沙德走，他们会对我做什么？
The police didn't let Harshad go, what will they do to me?
不，什么都不会发生
No, nothing will happen.
- 一切都结束了-不
- Everything is over. - No.
- 不，真的，一切都结束了-不
- No, really, everything is over. - No.
你说得对，我不能再这样生活下去了
You're right. I won't be able to live like this.
- 我不能这样活着，躲在恐惧中-拉希尔..
- I can't live like this, hiding in fear. - Rahil...
[法官]“你确定你已经完成了所有的调查吗? ”
[Judge] 'Are you sure you have completed all your investigations?'
是的，先生
[CBI Attorney] 'Yes, sir.'
好了，梅塔先生，你的保释现在被批准了
[Judge] 'Okay, Mr. Mehta, your bail is sanctioned now.'
别担心，好吗? 和乔蒂出去玩几天
[Ashwin] 'Don't worry, okay? Go out for a few days with Jyoti.'
梅塔先生我们是执法局的
Mr. Mehta, we are from the Enforcement Directorate.
我们以违反《外汇管理法》逮捕你
We are arresting you for breaking the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act...
根据第35条和第62条
...under section 35 and 62.
-请...-你有搜查令吗？
- So please... - Do you have a warrant?
- 逮捕他-逮捕令？
- Arrest him. - Warrant?
给我们看文件，邦主律师，和他们谈谈
Show us the papers. Lawyer saheb, talk to them.
你是说你在任何一家瑞士银行都没有账户？
So you're saying you don't have any account in any swiss bank?
我没有
No, I don't.
那么，你怎么把钱转移到国外呢？
So then, how do you transfer your money abroad?
- 通过洗钱?-什么？
- By laundering money? - What?
我们可以在几分钟内获得你们接线员的详细资料
We can get the details of your operator in minutes.
我没有任何人为我洗钱
I don't have anybody who launders money for me.
- 所以你没有接线员?-没有
- So you don't have an operator? - No, I don't.
那么，莫汉 · 拉尔是谁呢？
Who is this Mohan Lal, then?
你的一个前雇员用了他的名字
One of your ex-employees took his name...
你不是在开市那天派他去的吗？
...didn't you send him there on the day of the market opening?
莫汉拉尔 · 米萨瓦拉
Mohanlal S. Mithaiwala.
他是个糖果师，不是洗钱的
He is a confectioner. Not a money launderer.
很明显，你的消息来源有问题
It's so clear that your source is deaf.
“我们不能再继续关押哈萨德了”
[Das] 'We can't keep Harshad locked up anymore.'
他已经被执法局拘留五周了
'He's been in ED's custody for five weeks.'
回答法庭和媒体的问题可能会很困难
It can get tough to answer the court and the media.
所有人都被保释了，即使是 SBI 的人
Everyone has been released on bail. Even the SBI people.
我们还能把哈萨德关多久？
...How much longer can we keep Harshad locked up?
[ Swami ]“那就让他走吧”
[Swami] 'Let him go then.'
如果你不能再继续关押，那就这样吧... ..
'If you can't lock him up physically, so be it...'
至少，你可以在精神上束缚住他
'...at least, you can tie him down mentally.'
“提醒他不要散布有关首相的谣言”
'Remind him not to spread rumours about the Prime Minister.'
如果他再犯这样的错误..
'And if he makes such a mistake again...'
’ ... 他将被控告更多的罪行，更多的案件... ’
'...he will be accused for so many more crimes in so many more cases...'
他会在监狱里呆上10到15年
'...that he'll spend 10 to 15 years in jail.'
- 好的 Swami 先生
- Okay, Swami ji. - Hari Om.
“哈沙德大哥.. ... ”
[crowd] 'Harshad Bhai...'
哈沙德大哥
'Harshad Bhai...'
Harshad Bhai...
哈沙德大哥！
Harshad Bhai!
我的儿子！
My son!
让我驱散那恶毒的眼睛
Let me ward off the evil eye.
小混蛋！
Rascals!
你变得这么虚弱..
How weak you've become...
在那里睡不着觉，对不对？
You couldn't sleep there, right?
我在新闻上看到你用鞋子当枕头睡在地板上..
I read in the news that you slept on the floor using shoes as a pillow...
- 哦，妈咪!-别说了，妈妈..
- Oh, Mummy! - Stop it, Mummy...
- 去吃点东西然后睡觉-好的
- Go, eat something and go to sleep. - Yes.
我做了拉普西麦片粥
I've made lapsi. porridge
妈妈，请告诉我她没有做茄子泥和茄子粥
Mummy, please tell me she didn't make an eggplant mash with lapsi. brinjal/ porridge
因为已经被我碾碎了
Because I have already been mashed.
他还是那么幽默
He hasn't lost his humour.
去吧，乔蒂
Go, Jyoti.
很多水果，梅塔先生
'Lots of fruits, Mr. Mehta.'
你变得非常注重健康了
'You've become quite health conscious.'
橘子，最近我很喜欢橘子
Oranges. These days I'm loving oranges.
你在监狱里吃过饭吗？
Have you ever had prison food?
你喝过监狱的水吗？
Have you ever had water there?
你见过监狱里面什么样吗？
Have you ever seen the inside of a jail?
即使是我的敌人，我也不希望他们经历这些
I don't wish that even for my enemy.
我满怀信心地走了进去
I went in with such pride.
但四个月后..
But in four months...
我已经完全泄气了
I've been completely deflated.
然后我明白了..
And then I've understood...
”健康就是财富”的意思
...what "Health is wealth" means.
我也明白..
And I've also understood...
关键时刻还是要靠自己
...that I will only have to help myself.
不是这样的
That's not true.
你的朋友在你需要的时候帮助了你
Your friends helped you when you needed it.
哈沙德，你来德里却不告诉我？
Harshad, you came to Delhi and didn't tell me?
你应该先打个电话
You could've called.
我从别人那里得知你的到来，真是奇怪
It's strange that I get to know from others about your arrival.
你只告诉你的朋友
You only inform your friends about your plans.
朋友
Friends.
- 请吃点东西-谢谢
- Please have something. - Thank you. Thank you.
补钙，你应该多吃点
It's good for calcium, you should have.
你在JPC的朋友也找过我
Your friends from the JPC have also summoned me.
真是巧啊..
And what a coincidence...
你在同一时间想起了我
You thought of me at the exact same time.
在我出现在议会委员会之前，你突然出现了
Before I appear at the parliamentary committee, you appeared here.
我知道，在JPC
I realise. At the JPC...
如果出现了首相的名字
...if any names pop up, the PM...
斯瓦米先生就有麻烦了
...and Swami ji will be in trouble.
告诉我一些事情
[Harshad] 'Tell me something.'
他们是担心我还是担心他们自己？
Are they worried for me or themselves?
哈沙德，现在委员会已经有很多名字了
Harshad, a lot of names have already been taken before the JPC.
不应该有更多的名字
There shouldn't be any more names.
这对大家都有好处
It's in everybody's best interest.
尤其是对你
Especially yours.
对
Right.
我不会说出任何名字
I won't take any names.
只要你一直保护我
As long as you keep protecting me.
当然，哈尔沙德
Of course, Harshad.
好吧，我就说你来这里想说的
Okay, I'll say what you came here to say.
我不会提到首相
I won't mention the Prime Minister.
你看，在这些所谓的启示之后..
You see, after these so-called revelations...
很多人都给这个骗局起了不同的名字
...various people have given various names to the scam.
最初，它被称为股票骗局
Initially, it was called the stock scam.
经纪人不喜欢这样，所以他们称之为银行骗局
Brokers didn't like it so they called it the bank scam.
但如果要我说
But I will tell you what it is.
这就是花旗的骗局
It is the Citi scam.
花旗银行是这个系统中所有非法活动的集中地
Citibank is the beehive of all the illegal activities in the system.
让我们看看印度的货币市场
Let's just look at our Indian money markets.
在印度货币市场，像花旗银行这样的外国银行可以随心所欲地管理资金
In the Indian money market, foreign banks like Citibank rule as they wish.
而且他们还赚了一大笔钱
And they mint a ton of money.
花旗银行有财力
Citibank has all the money...
去购买所有新发行的政府债券
...to buy every new issue of every government bonds.
他们在市场上占有最大的份额
They have the lion's share in the market.
因此，一旦他们垄断了所有的证券，所有散户都将任由他们摆布
So once they corner all the securities, all the small players are at their mercy.
这还不是全部
And that's not all.
花旗银行确保..
Citibank makes sure...
它在市场上保持着支配地位
...that it maintains a dominant position in the market.
他们是怎么做到的呢？
And how do they do it?
利用系统中的漏洞..
By exploiting the loopholes in the system...
通过违反 RBI 的指导方针..
By violating RBI guidelines...
通过影响德里的政策制定
...and by influencing policy-making in Delhi...
通过他们强大的顾问委员会
...through their powerful advisory boards.
超过80% 的交易涉及复杂的财团
More than 80 percent transactions have sophisticated syndicates involved.
他们不让外人进入
They don't let outsiders enter.
他们可以很容易地利用..
And they can easily exploit...
缓慢而无知的印度银行系统
...the slow and ignorant Indian banking system.
甚至没有人理解这一点
No one even understands this.
很少有像苏切塔 · 达拉尔这样的记者提出这个问题
Very few journalists like Sucheta Dalal have brought it out.
我愿意帮忙
I'm willing to help.
整个真相都会大白于天下
The whole truth will be out.
我已经准备好和所有的调查机构合作了
I'm ready to cooperate with all the investigative agencies.
但前提是免除我所有的罪名
But only if I'm exonerated from all the charges.
如果我是你的话..
If I was in your shoes...
... 首先，我会调查 PMS 交易
...to start with, I'd be looking into PMS deals.
花旗银行的
PMS. Portfolio management services...
投资组合管理服务
...of Citibank.
一旦你开始调查，你就会明白为什么花旗银行是主脑... ..
Once you do that you'll realise why Citibank is the kingpin...
印度所有可疑的 PMS 交易
...of all the dubious PMS deals in India.
特亚吉先生，我不想浪费时间
Mr. Tyagi, I will not waste time.
让我们开门见山吧
Let us get straight to the point.
现在对贵行有严重的指控
There are severe allegations against your bank.
什么样的指控？
What kind of allegations?
贵行和其他银行一样，也有违规行为
Your bank is involved in irregularities like other banks.
比如说？
For example?
关于PMS违规行为，例如..
Irregularities regarding PMS, for example...
你可以翻我们所有的账簿，我没什么好隐瞒的
You can go through all our books. I have nothing to hide.
事实上，我可以亲自帮助你更好地理解我的账簿
In fact, I can personally assist you to get a better understanding of my books.
我们所有的交易，每一笔交易，都严格按照..
All our deals, every single one of them, are in strict accordance...
印度储备银行制定的指导方针
...with the guidelines set by the Reserve bank of India.
我们从来没有藐视过任何一条规则
We have never flouted a single rule.
你应该知道，我们已经看到..
You should know that we have already seen...
... 你的一些账簿，并发现了一些问题
...some of your books and have several issues with it.
但恕我直言，先生..
But with due respect, sir...
... 在财务问题上的误解是很自然的
...misunderstandings are natural in financial matters.
由于没有充分了解，可能会产生误解
There can be misinterpretation because of ignorance and...
你是说我们无知吗，特亚吉先生？
Are you calling us ignorant, Mr. Tyagi?
不是的，我相信你们都是很有学问的人
Not at all. I'm sure you all are very learned men.
但我们也是花旗银行
But we are also Citibank.
我们在印度已经有90年了
We have been in India since 90 years.
我们对这个国家非常忠诚
We are very committed to this country.
我们已经投入了大笔资金
We have invested large sums of money.
过去四年我们甚至没有分过红利
We haven't even taken any dividend for the last four years.
我们在这个国家培育了 NRI 的投资
We have nurtured the NRI investment in this country.
我们把数字设备公司带到了这个国家
We brought the Digital equipment corporation to this country.
我不明白为什么成功在这里是一种犯罪
I don't understand why being successful is such a crime here.
你确定 CBI 在跟踪你吗
[Venkitarajan] 'Are you sure the CBI is following you?'
“确定，我也在我家附近见过他们”
[Sucheta] 'Yes, I've seen them near my house too.'
那我们就不能这样见面了
Then, we can't meet like this.
但是还有一个人有兴趣见你
But there is someone else who is interested in meeting you.
不用说，这次会议是非正式的
Needless to say, this meeting will be unofficial.
你今天能去德里吗？
Can you go to Delhi today?
我想你应该去见一见
I think you should go. It could be an interesting meeting.
CBI、政府和媒体..
CBI, government and media...
都把注意力集中在一个人身上
...are after one man.
但我认为我们应该转移注意力
But I think we should shift the focus.
银行、国际银行..
Banks, International banks...
还有国有企业
...and government-owned companies.
JPC的权力有限
JPC has limited powers.
我们也不是一个调查机构
And we are not an investigative body also.
我们掌握了大量信息，但却无能为力
'We have tons of information but we can do nothing with it.'
严格来说，我们不能公开
Technically, we can't make it public.
但是你可以找到一种能让真相曝光的方式
But you can find a way to make it reach your readers.
一旦曝光..
Once it's out...
中央调查局就会介入调查
...the CBI will have to investigate.
没有任何借口
They will have no excuse.
这些不仅仅是文件，而是系统的真相
These are not just files, but the truth of the system. Truth.
但是，你只能在这个房间里看
But yes, you can only do it in this room.
你不能把任何东西带出这个房间
You can't take anything out of this room.
辛格先生还有更多的文件
Mr. Singh has more files.
他下午拿过来
He's getting it in the afternoon.
给你，还需要什么就告诉我好吗？
Here you are. You need anything else, let me know, okay?
有一些外资银行认为他们可以逃脱惩罚
There are some foreign banks who thought they would get away with anything.
玩弄银行收据，甚至没有保留记录以供核实
They made a mockery of bank receipts and did not even maintain proper records for verification.
他们大量证券交易的一些文件都是... ..
Some of the documents of bulk of their securities deals are...
消失了
...conveniently missing.
你可以查看所有的文件，然后问我任何你想问的问题
You can check all the papers and ask me anything you like.
[ Sucheta ]“当我们深入研究JPC的报告和记录时... ... ”
[Sucheta] 'As we dug deep into the JPC reports and records...'
“很明显，哈尔沙德 · 梅塔的骗局... ... ”
'...it became very clear that the Harshad Mehta scam...'
只是庞大银行系统违规行为的一小部分
'...was a part of the bigger irregularities in the banking system.'
“哈沙德并没有创造违规手段... ... ”
'Irregularities and flaws that Harshad didn't invent...'
“ ... 但他确实滥用了漏洞”
'...but he misused them freely.'
“还有一点很清楚”
'Another thing was clear.'
与哈尔沙德•梅塔(Harshad Mehta)一样，调查银行也很重要... ..
'Along with Harshad Mehta, it was important to investigate banks...'
特别是花旗银行及其经纪人
'...especially Citibank and its brokers.'
这是彻底清理系统的唯一方法
'This was the only way to clean the system completely.'
先生，我同意我们的一些交易看起来有问题..
Sir, I agree some of our dealings may look problematic...
我们可能遭受了巨大的损失
...and we may have suffered some big losses.
但我向你保证，先生..
But let me assure you, sir...
我们的 PMS 客户和老客户都没有损失
...that none of our PMS clients or our regular customers have lost any money.
饶先生，这不仅仅关乎利润和损失
Mr. Rao, it's not only about profits and losses.
人们一直在质疑你在货币市场上的运作方式
People have been questioning the way you are operating in the money market.
大家都在说，花旗银行是个恶霸
Everyone is saying, Citibank is a bully.
先生，那些说我们是恶霸的人..
Sir, the people who are calling us a bully...
都是那些无法与我们竞争的人
...are the same people who probably couldn't compete with us.
让我帮您快速回忆一下，先生..
Let me refresh your memory quickly, sir...
我们有多爱国
...of how patriotic we are...
以及我们对这个国家有多忠诚
...and what our allegiance to this country means, to us.
1990年，两年前..
1990, just two years back...
当印度被美国贸易代表卡拉・希尔斯控制的时候
...when India was under the hammer of US trade representative Carla Hills...
在国际收支危机期间
...during the balance of payments crisis.
是我坚决支持印度
It was I who stood strongly for India...
反对美国威胁实施贸易制裁
...against the USA threat of trade sanctions.
如果你还记得的话，先生，我们刊登了整版的亲印度广告
If you remember, sir, we ran full-page pro-India advertisements.
只是为了证明我们有多爱国
Just to show how patriotic we are.
然而，现在你却叫我们外国人
And look, today you are calling us foreigners.
无论如何，我会尽我所能..
Anyway. I'm going to do my best and...
我会试着用我们的行动来满足你，先生
...I'll try and satisfy you with our actions, sir.
希望如此
I hope so.
这些JPC的小丑一定是把消息泄露给了媒体
These buffoons from the JPC must have leaked the information to the press.
这些小丑对印度的商业模式一无所知
These jokers are clueless about how business is done in India.
我暂时搞定了财政部长
Now I may have handled the Finance Minister for the time being.
但是因为我们所有的文件都经过了严格的审查..
But since all our documents are under intense scrutiny...
媒体听证会随时都可能举行
...a press hearing can happen anytime.
但是这些事情确实发生了
But these things happen.
没有必要担心
There's no need to worry.
再过几天，印度和巴基斯坦将举行板球比赛
In a few days, there will be a cricket match between India and Pakistan...
印度将击败巴基斯坦
...where India is going to defeat Pakistan...
就这样，大家都会开心的
That's it. Everyone will be happy.
他们会忘记一切
They will forget everything.
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
听着，是时候向前看了
Look, it's time for you to move on.
你想说什么？
What are you trying to say?
- 你是要我辞职吗-不是
- Are you asking me to resign? - No.
我不是要你辞职
I'm not asking you to resign.
你是我们的明星
You've been our star performer.
你从财政部为我们赚了一大笔钱
You have earned us a fortune from the treasury department.
我是希望你能远离这次调查
'I just want you to stay away from this investigation.'
所以恭喜你
So congratulations.
你被提拔到纽约总部了
You've been promoted and moved to New York.
-不会吧？！-是的
- You're not serious. - I am.
现在我要点菜单上最贵的酒
And now I'm going to order the most expensive wine on the menu.
你来买单
And unfortunately, you're going to be paying for it.
我希望你带了信用卡
I hope you're carrying your card.
这里是印度
This is India.
我们只用现金
I only deal in cash.
你要在这种情况下去美国？
You're going to America in the middle of all this?
不是度假，管理层已经决定..
Not for a holiday. The management has decided this...
这对我们大家都好
...and it's the best for all of us.
对大家都好？
All of us? Ah!
还是对你和你的银行好？
Or for you and your bank?
我们的办公室和住宅正遭到搜查
Our offices and homes are being raided.
正在调查我们的账目
They are looking into our accounts.
甚至逮捕了我，该死的，我还进了监狱
They even arrested me, goddamn it! I was in jail.
- 但现在你出来了-是啊，保释了
- But now you're out. - Yeah, but on bail.
你知道他们提起了多少诉讼吗？
Do you have any idea how many cases they have filed against us?
我不确定，但是没有他们起诉哈萨德的那么多
I'm not sure, but not as many as they have filed against Harshad.
现在你觉得这很好笑了？
So now you think this is funny?
好了，AK! 放松
Come on, AK! Relax.
这个体系是有缺陷的
The system is flawed.
你不能对体系提起诉讼
And you can't file a case against a system.
不能逮捕系统
You can't arrest a system.
这一切很快就会平息下来
All this is going to die down soon.
保持低调
Just keep a low profile.
我得走了，杰瑞在等我
I must go now. Jerry is waiting for me.
但是你们要保持联系，一切顺利
But you stay in touch. All the best.
在联合议会委员会之前，他甚至没有放过花旗银行..
Before the Joint Parliamentary Committee, he didn't even let Citibank go...
他会拿我们怎么办？
What will he do with us?
等着瞧吧..
Wait and watch...
等时机成熟，他会像电影英雄一样挺身而出
...when the time is right, he'll come forward like a film hero...
把我们都供出来
...and rat us all out.
哈尔沙德不是我们的敌人
Harshad is not our enemy.
但是他应该知道他有很多敌人
But he should know he has a lot of enemies.
虽然我们不能把他送回监狱，但他应该永远害怕回去
Though we can't send him back to jail, he should always fear going back.
他应该每天做关于监狱的噩梦
He should have nightmares about jail.
进来吧
Come in. Come on.
开始，开始
Start, start.
- 这是干什么? 阿什温!-搜查每个角落
- What is this? Ashwin! - Search every bloody corner.
发生什么事了，长官？
What's going on, sir?
我们有搜查令
We have a search warrant.
你家不是散步的海滨大道
Your house is not Marine Drive, that we have come here for a stroll.
- 我们有可靠消息-什么消息？
- We have some solid information. - What information?
发生了什么？
What happened?
你认识尼拉杰·沙阿吗？
Do you know Niraj Shah?
我们见过几次面
We have met a couple of times.
几次？
A couple of times?
根据我们的消息，你们两家关系很好
According to our information, your families are very close.
还一起去度假
You go on holidays together.
我们有共同的旅行策划人，是在一次假期中认识的
We have a common tour operator. We met during a holiday.
高摩也会为他们理财，对吧？
Growmore handles their investments too, right?
也许吧
Maybe.
你知道我们有多少客户吗？
Do you have any idea how many clients we have?
你知道尼拉杰做毒品生意吗？
Do you have any idea that Niraj has a narcotics business?
我们怎么知道？
How would we know?
他做什么生意，跟我们有什么关系？
And what business he does, how does it concern us?
不管与你有没有关系，我们来做决定，梅塔先生
Whether it concerns you or not, we will decide that, Mr. Mehta.
但如果你知道什么..
But if you know anything...
自愿告诉我们
...tell us voluntarily.
或者，你也知道我们可以再联系起来
Or, you know that we can make the connection.
根本没有联系
It will have to be a made-up connection, because in reality there is none.
梅塔先生，缉毒科..
Mr. Mehta, narcotics...
不像是股票市场的骗局
...is not like a share market scam.
你一定听说过 COFEPOSA
You must have heard about COFEPOSA.
保护外汇和防止走私活动法
Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention of Smuggling activities Act.
如果你被起诉，你可以忘记过正常的生活
If you are charged with this, you can forget about living a normal life.
我不是... 我不是在开玩笑好吗？
And I am not... I am not f*****g around, okay?
先生，我们什么也没找到
[CBI officer] 'Sir, we didn't find anything.'
哦！
Oh!
这是可卡因... 不是你在厨房里可以找到的油炸小吃
It's cocaine... not snacks that you'll find frying in the kitchen.
没有人在家经营毒品生意
No one conducts narcotics business from home.
我希望你没有忘记我们的办公室
I hope you haven't forgotten our office.
如果你想起什么，请来找我们
If you remember anything, please pay us a visit.
如果我们发现了什么，我会再把你关进去
And if we find something, we'll take you away.
好吗？
Okay?
- 大家快点，我们走-是，长官
- Come on, everybody. Let's move. -[Officer] 'Yes, Sir.'
缉毒科？
Narcotics?
这是怎么回事？
What is going on?
如果让他们安排，他们下一步就会称我们为恐怖分子
Left to them, they'll call us terrorists next.
我们应该做好准备，接下来，他们会经常来突袭
We should get prepared. Now, they will regularly raid us.
我们有摄像机，不是吗? 在哪里？
We had a video camera, didn't we? Where is it?
你用摄像机做什么？
What will you do with a video camera?
我要拍一部电影
I'll make a film.
哈尔沙德？
Harshad?
我录这段视频是因为..
I'm recording this video because...
如果我出了什么事，人们应该知道谁该为此负责
...if anything happens to me, people should know who is responsible.
斯瓦米已经和我们断绝了一切关系，对吗？
Swami ji has severed all ties with us, right?
现在是时候..
Now it's time...
把那个大师从冥想中唤醒
...to wake that Swami from his meditation.
政府和斯瓦米都应该知道..
The government and Swami should both know...
哈沙德的不幸也会给他们蒙上阴影
...that Harshad's bad luck can also cast a shadow on them.
如果他们想搞我……
If they try to f*** with me...
整个国家会搞死他们
...the whole country will f*** them over.
我知道中央调查局是怎么运作的
I know how CBI works.
它们被德里的皮带拴着
They are on Delhi's leash, and they bark on command.
普拉纳夫，你真是个傻瓜
Pranav, you're a fool.
你一开始就应该带他来见我
You should have brought him to me right in the beginning.
那些自称出庭律师的蠢货.
Those foolish lawyers who call themselves barristers...
连西装都不会穿
...and don't even know how to wear a coat properly...
你为什么要去找他们？
Why did you have to go to them?
拉姆叔叔，你是司法之神
Ram uncle, you're the god of the judiciary.
我们觉得这件事太小了，不值得上帝去操心
We felt this was too small a matter, to trouble God with.
我们不知道这场战争会持续到
We didn't know this war would drag on for so long...
PMO进入战场
...that the PMO would enter the battlefield.
于是我以上帝的名义把哈沙德带到这里
So I took God's name and brought Harshad here.
别再用上帝这个词来讨好我了
Stop buttering me up with this 'God' business.
这段时间，你一直生活在上帝的怜悯之中
All this while, you were living on god's mercy.
但是现在你得依法办事了
But now you'll have to work with the law.
哈沙德..
Harshad...
你给首相的一千万
...the one crore that you gave the PM...
有跟别人提过吗？
...did you tell anyone about it?
还没有
Not yet.
- 但我可以证明-我的工作就是证明
- But I can prove it. - It's my job to prove.
我是你的律师
I'm your lawyer.
听着，现在..
And listen, now...
警察局和中央调查局，不管他们问什么
...the police, CBI... whatever they ask...
“没有我的允许，你不能开口”
'You will not talk to them without consulting me.'
“你明白吗? ”
'Do you understand?'
1991年11月2日到4日，你提取了一些大额款项
In 1991, between 2nd and 4th November, you made some large withdrawals.
从格林德莱斯银行提现100万卢比
Ten lakh rupees from Grindlays Bank, Fort branch.
从印度国家银行提现300万卢比
Thirty lakhs from SBI's main branch.
还有11月4日在德里的两次提现
And two withdrawals in Delhi on 4th November.
450万卢比
Forty-five lakhs.
你怎么会有这么多现金？
What were you doing with so much cash?
我什么都不记得了，这些都是很久以前的交易
I don't remember anything. These are very old transactions.
这是一大笔钱，梅塔先生
It's a big amount, Mr. Mehta.
试着回忆一下
Try to remember.
听着，这对你来说可能是一大笔钱，但对我来说不是
Look, this might be a big amount for you, not for me.
我真的不记得了
I really don't remember.
如果你想起来的话记得告诉我
Let me know if you remember.
你不应该在那里说一个字
You shouldn't have uttered a single word there.
你为什么让他说话？
Why did you let him speak?
- 你不明白吗?-但我说什么了？
- Don't you understand? - But what did I say?
你不是说你不记得钱的事了吗？
Didn't you say that you don't remember anything about the money?
所以‘我不记得了’并不意味着我说了什么
So 'I don't remember' doesn't mean I said anything.
你不知道他们是怎么把这个‘我不记得’变成证据的
You have no idea how they can turn this 'I don't remember' into evidence.
幸好中央调查局的审讯记录在法庭上不能作为证据
Thank God CBI's interrogation is not admissible in court.
否则你就废了
Or you would have let the PM off the hook.
无论如何
Anyway.
我会处理好这个达斯局长
I will take care of this Das.
怎么做？
How?
致中央调查局局长达斯先生
To Mr. KS Das, CBI Chief.
中央调查局询过问我的委托人
The cash withdrawals made by my client...
哈沙德・尚蒂拉尔・梅塔先生
...Mr. Harshad Shantilal Mehta...
在1991年11月2日和4日之间
...between 2nd and 4th November, 1991...
提取的现金
...about which CBI questioned him...
这个问题是政治敏感的
...are politically sensitive in nature...
“ ... 梅塔先生可以透露有关现金的用途... ”
'...and Mr. Mehta can disclose details regarding them...'
... 除非他能免受政治迫害
'...only if he gets immunity from political persecution.'
- Kiran?-怎么了？
- Kiran? - Yeah?
你读过《商业标准》的新报道了吗？
Did you read Business Standard's new story?
- 什么报道?-他们发表了一封信..
- What story? - They have published a letter...
杰斯马拉尼写信给中央调查局局长
...that Jethmalani wrote to the CBI chief.
他在信中宣称哈沙德可能贿赂了在政府里很有权势的人
In it, he alleges that Harshad might have paid off someone...
大概一千万左右
...very powerful in the government. Around one crore or something.
称之为政治敏感
Calls it politically sensitive.
你知道可能是谁吗？
Do you have any idea who it might be?
所以现在你也开始在媒体上制造谣言
'So now you're creating rumours in the press also?'
我不做这么冒险的空头头寸，我是大公牛
I don't take such risky short positions. I am the big bull.
现在，我只是制造了一个谣言
For now, I've just created a rumour.
但是搞不好... 首相可能会失去他的价值和他的政府..
But you never know... the Prime Minister might lose both his value and his government...
你真的认为，如果这些无稽之谈公之于众，会有所不同吗？
Do you really think, if this nonsense goes public, it will make a difference?
你觉得..
Do you think...
你是来喝橙汁的吗？
...you've been sent here to drink orange juice?
你是来谈判的对吧？
You're here to negotiate, right?
所有指控我们的案件都必须撤销
All the cases against us should be withdrawn.
梅塔先生，我们没有魔杖..
Mr. Harshad Mehta, we don't have a magic wand...
可以让一切在一夜之间消失
...which can make everything disappear overnight.
所得税，中央调查局，媒体，每个人都在追查你..
Income tax, CBI, press, everyone is after you...
我知道... 所有人都在追查我
I know... Everyone is after me.
有时候我觉得，他们甚至会起诉我在证交所扔炸弹
Sometimes I feel, they'll even accuse me of the bomb blast at BSE.
CBI 已经用 COFEPOSA 威胁我了
CBI is already threatening me with COFEPOSA.
他们还会以 TADA 罪起诉我
They'll charge me with TADA too.
一定会有些斡旋余地的
There has to be some middle ground.
你一定要把嘴闭严
You just keep your mouth zipped.
我看看能帮上什么忙
I'll see how you can be helped.
我要书面的
I want it in writing.
以书面形式？
In writing?
- 这是 Jethmalani 先生的主意吗?-他是我们的律师
- Is this Mr. Jethmalani's idea? - He's our lawyer.
当然，他会考虑我们的安全
Naturally, he will think about our safety.
我要书面的
I want it in writing.
不可能用书面形式给出任何东西
It's impossible to give anything in writing.
“我们只能做到这种程度”
'This is all that we can offer.'
现在你来决定，你想怎么样？
Now you decide. What would you like to do?
有这样的人群和这样的热情..
With this kind of a crowd and this kind of a heat...
让我结束所有的猜测，盖棺论定
...let me put an end to all the speculations and make it official.
这个骗局是
The scam was encouraged...
由政府发起和支持的
...initiated and sustained by the government.
一千万现金支付给了尊敬的纳拉辛哈·拉奥
The money of rupees one crore was paid to honourable PV Narasimha Rao...
印度总理
...the Prime Minister of India.
手提箱和钱都按照总理的指示
And the suitcase and the money was left with Mr. Khandekar...
留给了坎德卡先生..
...the personal assistant to the Prime Minister...
首相的私人助理
...at the Prime Minister's suggestion.
人们不会给骗局以人命名
People don't give any human name to scams.
但如果这个骗局要用人的名字..
But if a human name is to be given to this scam...
这不是哈尔沙德·梅塔的骗局
...it is not the Harshad Mehta scam.
这是总理的骗局
It is a PV Narasimha Rao scam.